Guide to the Records of the Office of the President (Dr. James McNaughton Hester) RG.3.0.7
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of the President (Dr. James McNaughton Hester)
1951-1977
New York University Archives
RG.3.0.7
59 Linear Feet in 103 manuscript boxes and 4 record cartons
The papers of James M. Hester contain administrative memoranda, correspondence, reports, publications, press releases, and newspaper clippings produced while he was president of NYU from 1962 to 1975. During Hester's 13-year tenure, NYU experienced revolutionary developments that changed forever the goals, statements, actions, and appearance of the University. Subjects covered in this collection include the sale of the Bronx campus, student protests, and severe financial crises within the University.
This collection consists of the administrative files of James McNaughton Hester, president of New York University from 1962-1975.
Arrangement
Series I, II, III, VI, XI, and XII are arranged alphabetically. Series IV and V are arranged according to a numbering system used by Hester's office. Series VII, VIII, IX, and X are arranged by subject. Series XIII is, with some exceptions, mainly chronologically arranged. See individual series descriptions for more details.
The collection is organized into 13 series:
Alphabetical
Administration
Associations
Development
Governance
Government Relations
Finance
Facilities and Services
Personnel
Public Relations
Schools and Divisions
Student Affairs
Interviews, Speeches, and Testimony, 1962-1975
Scope and Content Note
The collection of papers created under Dr. James M. Hester as President of New York University encompasses a difficult and transitional period in the University's history. Composed of memoranda, correspondence, reports, publications, press releases, and newspaper clippings, these papers represent the official response of the University in many matters.
As top administrative officer of the University, Dr. Hester required information from all aspects of the University's structure to make informed decisions. Correspondence, reports, and publications concerning the various schools, divisions, departments, students groups, alumni concerns, and faculty organizations comprise a number of files in this collection.
Hester's office used two filing systems to organize its records. Records dating from 1962 to 1969 were arranged alphabetically by folder title. After 1969 the files were grouped into 12 categories: Administration, Associations, Alumni Affairs, Development, Governance, Government Relations, Finance, Facilities and Services, Personnel, Public Relations, Schools and Divisions, and Student Affairs. Because the records created before 1969 represented the same informational categories, the archives decided to incorporate the earlier files into the groupings established after 1969. Each category forms a series with the addition of another series of alphabetical files. Due to the fact that Alumni Affairs constituted only two folders, it was integrated into the Administration series. See series descriptions for more detailed explanations of the kinds of information present.
Historical Note
The Office of the President is the top administrative office and is responsible for the efficient management of the entire University. The President must carefully attend to the following major considerations: effective administration, including the development, implementation, and monitoring of university activities; the cultivation of outreach programs; and the promotion of university activities to prospective donors and the general public.
On December 16, 1955, the New York State Board of Regents amended the University Charter, forcing a number of terminology changes. The title of the chief executive of the University changed from Chancellor to President on July 1, 1956. The Board of Trustees adopted a measure providing for a Chancellor and Executive Vice-President who would serve as a general advisor to the President and perform duties in the President's absence. The Director for the University Budget and Assistant Director of the Budget for research service would assist the Executive Vice-President.
Dr. Hester came from Long Island University to NYU in 1960. For the next two years he served as the dean of the Graduate School of Arts and Science and Executive Dean of Arts and Sciences. In 1962 he became president. Hester's term encompassed a number of important events in the history of the University. Chief among these were the student activities of the 1960s and the growth and transformation of the University into a prestigious urban educational institution.
NYU experienced severe financial difficulties during the 1960s caused in part by diminishing enrollment and subsequent loss of tuition money. Several strategies were proposed to solve the problem, including a plan to sell the Heights Campus in the Bronx. The closing of the Heights campus in 1973 caused some controversy. Opinions and comments of the faculty, staff, students, alumni, and the community at large are well-represented in correspondence found in Hester's papers.
Quelling student dissatisfaction during this time presented an enormous task. Numerous student groups demanded changes within the University. They conducted civil rights and anti-war protests as well as protests calling for administrative changes. In 1966 students responded to proposed tuition, fees, and dormitory rate increases with staged marches, boycotts, and sit-ins. As a result, the University allowed the inclusion of student representatives on committees and boards that dealt with fees, curriculum, and discipline. The administration's response to the concerns of the students is well-documented in the collection and serves as a source of information for student affairs of the period.
Through consolidation of its operations, changing its admission policies, and increasing its involvement in urban affairs, NYU transformed its institutional character. Following the sale of the Heights campus, NYU focused on developing its presence around Washington Square. The construction of Bobst Library allowed NYU to consolidate library and research collections formerly scattered over 36 locations. A more selective admission policy encouraged more full time students to attend and spurred the university to purchase residential facilities. Much information within the collection reflects this transformation, which began in the 1950s and continued through Hester's administration.
Dr. Hester resigned from the presidency in 1975 to become president of the United Nations University. During Hester's 13-year tenure, NYU experienced revolutionary developments that changed forever the goals, statements, actions, and perception of New York University.
Access Restrictions
Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Provenance
This collection of papers from the Office of the President during the administration of Dr. James McNaughton Hester came to the University Archives through four accessions made in 1978, 1979, 1980, and 1981, after initial inventories were completed by E. Frederick Knauth.
Composed of 43.5 linear feet of material contained in 87 Hollinger boxes, this collection of material spans the dates 1951-1975. The collection is in good condition. Numerous thermofaxed copies and newspaper clippings were photocopied onto acid-free paper and originals discarded.
A number of booklets, pamphlets, and large bulky reports were removed for storage separately. Some material is restricted. Numerous autographed letters were photocopied and the originals placed in the restricted access file. Also removed from this collection were a number of files concerning Board of Trustees members that were added to the Secretary's collection. Evaluations of various Deans have also been removed and stored separately for confidentiality. These two transfers took place as part of the inventories completed by Mr. Knauth.
Lectures.; Memorandums.; Pamphlets.; Private universities and colleges |x Administration |y 20th century.; Correspondence.; Articles.; Interviews.; Speeches.; New York University. Office of the President; New York University. Office of Public Affairs; New York University
- Series I: Alphabetical, 1961-1969 (Boxes 1-20)
  Scope and Contents note
  The alphabetical series consists of 100 linear inches of materials arranged alphabetically by correspondent. The files were arranged by Hester's office previous to the installation of the subject files and numbering system that began in 1969. Consequently this series represents every aspect of Hester's job as President of the University. There is correspondence with professors, students, the community, and prominent individuals.
  Files are arranged alphabetically by title, department, or individual name. General correspondence files include documents such as correspondence with the public and invitations to off-campus social events as well as communications with several individual correspondents. The broad folder titles may make it more difficult to locate desired subjects.
  - General Correspondence - A, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence - A - AL, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence - AM, 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence - AM, 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence - AM, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence - AN - AZ, 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Administrative Council, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Admissions, Office of, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - All Univeristy Departments, General, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - All University Departments - Still Committee, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - All University Departments, A-Z, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Alumni Federation, Alumni Fund, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Alumni Federation, Alumni Groups, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Alumni Federation, Alumni Groups, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Alumni Federation, Alumni Groups, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Alumni Federation, General Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Alumni Federation, Individual Alumni, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Alumni Federation, " "David Lipson, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Annual Report of the President, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Aphrodisas Excavation, 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Architect - Director of Planning & Supervising Architect, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Archivist, University, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Arts, School of, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Athletics, Division of, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence B, 1964-1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence B, 1964-1969 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence B, 1964-1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence BA-BE, 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence BI-BO, 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence BR-BZ, 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Board of Trustees, Correspondence, 1965-1967 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Brazilian Institute, 1962-1968 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence C, 1966-1969 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence CA-CG, 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence CH-CL, 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence CM-CZ, 1964-1968 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Center for International Affairs, 1965-1968 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Center for International Studies--ERIAA, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Chancellor and Executive Vice-President, 1964-1967 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Chancellors Office, Assistant Chancellor for Student Affairs, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Circular memos, 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Classified Research, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Commerce, School of, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Commission on Effective Use of Resources, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Communications Arts Group, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Continuing Education and Extension Services, School of, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Controller, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Council of Deans, General Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Council of Deans, General Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Courant Institute, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - General Correspondence DA-DI, 1966-1969 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence DI-DR, 1966-1969 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence DU-DY, 1965-1969 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Danforth Foundation, 1965-1966 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Dentistry, College of, 1965-1967 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Development, Office of, 1965-1966 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Development, Office of, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Development, Office of, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Development, Office of - Alumni Annual Giving Group, 1967-1969 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Development, Office of - Community Relations, 1965-1966 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Development, Office of - Public Relations Office, 1965-1967 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Development, Office of - "University Research and the City" correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - General Correspondence E-EDU, 1964-1969 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence EDU-EX, 1965-1967 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Education, School of, 1964-1966 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Education, School of, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Education, School of - Institute of Development Studies, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Education, School of - Nursing Program, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Engineering Science, School of, 1965-1968 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence FA-FD, 1964-1969 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence FE-FI, 1964-1969 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence FL-FO, 1965-1969 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence FR-FU, 1965-1967 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Faculty, General Correspondence, 1965-1967 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Committees, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Financial Aid, Dean of, 1965-1968 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Financial Aid, Dean of, 1966-1969 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - French House, 1965-1966 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Fund Board, 1967-1968 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence G-GRE, 1965-1967 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence GRO-GU, 1966-1967 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - General Education, Division of, 1965-1966 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, 1965-1968 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, 1964-1966 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Graduate School of Business Administration, 1964-1967 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Graduate School of Business Administration - University of Lagos, Nigeria, 1965-1968 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Graduate School of Public Administration, 1965-1966 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Graduate School of Public Administration, 1967-1968 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Graduate School of Social Work, 1965-1968 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Graduate Work, School of Engineering and Sciences and University College, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence H-HE, 1965-1967 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence HI-HU, 1966-1968 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence I, 1964-1967 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Institute for Computer Research in the Humanities, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Institute of Fine Arts, 1965-1967 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Institute of Hebrew Studies, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - International Student Center, 1967-1968 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence J, 1965-1968 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - General Correspondence K, 1965-1968 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - King, Martin Luther, Scholarship, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - King, Martin Luther, Scholarship, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - King, Martin Luther, Scholarship, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - King, Kartin Luther, Scholarship - Complaints, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - King, Martin Luther, Scholarship - other disadvantaged minorities, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - King, Martin Luther, Scholarship - Poor Peoples Campaign, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence L-LI, 1964-1968 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence LO-LU, 1966-1967 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Law, School of, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Law, School of, 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Law, School of - Selection of New Dean, 1966-1967 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Libraries, Correspondence, 1965-1967 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - General Correspondence M, 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence MA-MC, 1964-1967 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence ME-MI, 1964-1967 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence MH-MZ, 1964-1967 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Medical Center, Bellvue Hospital, 1967-1968 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Medical Center, General Correspondence, 1966-1968 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Medical Center Board, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Medical Center Board, 1964-1967 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Medical Center Board, Committees, 1965-1967 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Medical Center Board, Committees - Long Range Planning and Development, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Medical Center Institute of Rehabitation Medicine, 1967-1968 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Medical Center School of Medicine, 1966-1968 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Memoranda to Faculty, Staff, and Students, 1966-1972 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Metropolitian Leadership Program, 1964-1967 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Middle States Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools, 1965-1967 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Miller, Montgomery, Spaulding & Porth, 1966-1967 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence N, 1967-1969 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence NA, 1965-1968 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence NE-NZ, 1963-1967 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - New York City, General Correspondence, 1965-1967 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - New York State, General Correspondence, 1965-1967 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - New York State, Bundy Committee, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - New York State, Citizens Committee for an Effective Constitution, 1965-1966 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - New York State, Constitutional Convention RE: Travia Letter, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - New York State, Department of Mental Hygiene Proposed Institute on Alcholism, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - New York State, State University of New York - Board of Regents, 1964-1965 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - NYS, SUNY, City University of New York, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - NYS, SUNY, Engineer Shortage, 1966-1967 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - NYS, SUNY, Regents 92nd Convention, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - NYS, University of the State of New York - Board of Regents, 1966-1967 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - NYS,University of the State of New York - State Education Department, 1966-1967 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence O, 1965-1968 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence P, 1962-1967 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence P, 1967-1969 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Peace Corps, 1965-1966 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Placement Services, 1966-1967 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Plans Room, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Plant and Properties, 1966-1968 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Plant and Properties, Housing, Director of, 1965-1966 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Plant and Properties, Housing, Weinstein, 1966-1968 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Presidential Citations, 1966-1968 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Presidential Robe, 1961-1964 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Presidents office, Assistants to, 1965-1966 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Presidents Office, Assistants to - Student Affairs, 1965-1967 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Presidents Office, General Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Presidents Office, Presidents Council, 1965-1966 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Presidents Office, Special Assistant to, 1966-1967 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Press, University, 1966 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Provost, University, 1966-1967 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence Q, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence R, 1967-1969 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence RAB-ROB, 1964-1969 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence ROC-RUT, 1964-1969 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Registar, 1965-1968 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Religious Activities, Catholic Center, 1966-1967 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Religious Activities, General Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Religious Activities, Jewish Culture Foundation, 1965-1967 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Research Services, 1965-1966 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - ROTC, 1965-1967 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence S, 1966-1969 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence SA-SL, 1965-1969 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence SM-SZ, 1966-1969 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Senate Committee on Student Participation, 1966-1967 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Senate, University, Committees, 1962-1967 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Senate, University, Correspondence, 1965-1967 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Senate, University, Elected Groups, 1965-1967 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Sterling Forest, 1967 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Student Activities, 1965-1966 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Student Activities, 1967-1968 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Student Activities, AD-HOC Committee for a Democratic University, 1967-1968 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Student Activities, AD-HOC Committee to Oppose Tutition Increase, 1966-1968 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Student Activities, Black Allied Students Association, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Student Activities, Coffee Hours, 1966-1968 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Student Activities, Fraternities, 1964-1967 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Student Activities, General Correspondence, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Student Activities, Glee Club, 1965-1968 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Student Activities, Graduate Student Organizations, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Student Activities, Newspapers, 1967-1969 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Student Activities, Newspapers - Heights Daily News, 1964-1967 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Student Activities, Newspapers - Washington Square Journal, 1964-1968 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Student Activities, Presidental Forum, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Student Activities, Publications, 1965-1968 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Student Activities, Publications - Yearbooks, 1965-1967 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Student Activities, Recruitment, 1967-1969 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Student Activities, Religious Activities, 1967-1968 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Student Activities, Sororities, 1965-1967 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Student Activities, Students for a Democratic Society, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Student Activities, University Heights Center, 1965-1967 (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Student Activities, Whitman House, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Student Activities, WNYU Station, 1967-1968 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - General Correspondence TA-TE, 1965-1969 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence TH-TY, 1967-1969 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Treasurer, 1967-1968 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence U, 1965-1968 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - United States Government, 1965-1967 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - U.S. Government, Legislation, 1962-1963 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - U.S. Government, Legislation, 1964 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - U.S. Government, Legislation, 1964 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - U.S. Government, Legislation, 1965 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - U.S. Government, Legislation, 1965 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - U.S. Government, Legislation, 1966-1967 (Box 18, Folder 1)